以下内容提供
the following content is provided under
CreativeCommons许可您的支持
a Creative Commons license your support
将有助于MIT开放课程继续
will help MIT OpenCourseWare continue to
提供高质量的教育资源
offer high quality educational resources
免费
for free
捐款或查看额外的捐款
to make a donation or to view additional
数百个麻省理工学院课程的材料
materials from hundreds of MIT courses
访问位于ocw.mit.edu的麻省理工学院开放式课件
visit MIT opencourseware at ocw.mit.edu
好的，所以我希望我们能拥有
ok so I was hoping that we would have
准备下一个在线作业但是
the next online assignment ready but
Julia6新版本正在减缓我们的速度
Julia 6 the new version is slowing us
下来，它可能是下一次但是
down and it'd probably be next time but
我的讲座当然是我的
my lectures of course are well what I
想说或许这不是
want to say perhaps is this isn't
打算成为数学课程
intended to be a course in numerical
线性代数，但我以为我不能
linear algebra but I thought I couldn't
让整个学期过去
let the whole whole semester go by
没有说什么怎么样
without saying something about how to
计算特征值和奇异值
compute eigenvalues and singular values
当然你会打电话给AG或SVD或
of course you're gonna call AG or SVD or
它们相当于Python或Julia但是
they equivalent in Python or Julia but
实际上我们的QR分解
actually the QR factorization that we
谈到我们谈到完全关闭
spoke about that we spoke off entirely
关于上次是意外的关键
about last time is the key unexpectedly
你意外地有一个矩阵a
unexpectedly you have a matrix a whose
你想要的本征值让我们开始吧
eigen values you want so let's start
具有特征值，它可能是一个
with eigen values and it might be a
对称矩阵ii将留在
symmetric matrix i-i'll stay with a
而不是因为它没有
rather than s because it doesn't have to
是，但你得到特殊的总是你
be but you get special always you get
如果矩阵是特殊的东西
something special if the matrix is
对称确定所以这种计算方法
symmetric ok so this method of computing
至少对我来说是特征值，我想
eigen values to me at least and I think
有太多的人像这样出来了
too many people came like out of the
前一段时间的蓝色，但不久前
blue a while ago but not that long ago
而且效果很好
and it worked very well
所以
so
这就是它被称为QR的想法
here's the idea it's called the QR
方法，因为你从保理开始
method because you start by factoring
你的矩阵进入QR所以这是一个
your matrix into QR so here's a that's
我们可以称之为零
can we call it a zero
得到了一些我们从哪个矩阵开始
got some matrix we start with whose
我们想要的特征值，我会称之为
eigenvalues we want and I'll call these
Q0和R0，你还记得那是什么
Q 0 and R 0 and you remember what that
手段
means
那是什么躲在后面
what that what what's hiding behind
那些我写的你的信
those letters that I've written you have
像I一样可能对称的列
the columns of a possibly symmetric as I
说但不是正交通常所以你
said but not orthogonal usually so you
找到一个正交的基础
find an orthogonal basis you
将它们正交化它们
orthogonalize them you line them up
然后彼此垂直
perpendicular to each other and then
有一个矩阵R正好发生
there's a matrix R which is happens to
是连接上部的三角形
be upper triangular that connects the
与正交不正交
not orthogonal basis with the orthogonal
基础权利我们构建了我们的步骤
basis right we we constructed our step
一步一步然后想法是写这些
by step and then the idea is write these
以相反的顺序，这将是一个
in the reverse order and that will be a
1在下一个确定，然后再次做到这一点，
1 the next a ok and then do it again and
一次又一次
again and again
所以我们当然希望那个
and so we're hoping of course that the
特征值没有改变，我们希望如此
eigenvalues didn't change we hoping that
我们可以用1来忘记0再次开始
we can forget a 0 start again with a 1
并产生一个2并继续这样我们
and produce a 2 and continue so we're
希望有两件事不会有希望
hoping two things one will not be hope
我们可以看到特征值
we can see that the eigenvalues the
1和n的特征值是
eigenvalues of a 1 and a naught are the
相同的，所以我们并没有改变
same so we have not changed the
特征值如果你，我们怎么看？
eigenvalues how did we see that if you
不得不表明两个矩阵有
had to show that two matrices had the
你会计算所有相同的特征值
same eigenvalues would you compute all
特征值并比较他们
the eigenvalues and compare them he'll
当然不是你会做什么的
certainly not what would you do what's
通常的最佳测试通常的测试
the best test the usual test the usual
你想的东西展现给他们
thing you would want to show to they're
类似
similar
这是正确的，所以声称就是这样
that's right so the claim would be that
这两个矩阵是相似的权利，使
these two matrices are similar right so
也许我们应该表明我们想要的
maybe we should show that so we want to
以不同的方式写一个1所以这样
write a 1 in a different way so so the
声明是1是类似于我们只是
claim is a 1 is similar to a so we just
必须弄清楚我们必须得到1
have to figure out we have to get a 1
然后转到0所以这里是1ok所以1
and turn to a 0 so here is a 1 ok so a 1
那是我想表明那是对的
that's I want to show that that's right
所以这是我们的0Q0但是什么是Q0来自
so that's our 0 Q 0 but what is Q 0 from
这里Q0是我们的Q0是什么
here Q 0 is what we is our Q 0 is what
我想要将0反转
do I want I want to put our 0 inverse
所以我们的0现在为Q0我
over there so so our 0 now for Q 0 I'm
要替代究竟什么是Q0的我
gonna substitute so what is Q 0 its I
将该等式的两边乘以
multiply both sides of that equation by
我们的0逆，所以Q0是0对不起我
our 0 inverse so Q 0 is a 0 is sorry I
说a和写了一个000逆
said said a and wrote Q a 0 r 0 inverse
适合q0我适合它
right for for q0 i foot in what it
等于，而且已经完成了
equals and that's done it
那正是告诉我一个1
that's exactly telling me that a 1 which
这是等于这个，这是一个
is this equals this and that's a
相似性转换我没有
similarity transformation I have not
改变了特征值，这样就可以了
changed the eigen values so that's ok
这是喜欢你的另一件事
the other thing which is the like you
可以说这件事的奇迹是
could say the miracle in this thing is
当我继续这样做的时候
that when I continue to do that for
几乎每个矩阵都是矩阵开始的
almost every matrix the matrices begin
丢掉对角线上的东西
to lose stuff off the diagonal
尤其是在对角线以下
especially below the diagonal by the
命令QR完成它
ordering that that QR is done so it
你倾向于从矩阵a开​​始
you tend to you start with a matrix a
结你得到一个矩阵a1就像
knot you get a matrix a 1 which is like
这个部分有点小
a little smaller here this part being
坚果特别小，你再做一次
nuts especially smaller you do it again
这甚至更小，即便如此
this is even smaller even so I put even
小一个甚至更小，你保持
smaller a to even smaller and you keep
去而对于大多数矩阵结果
going and for most matrices the result
是我不知道我们有多少步骤
is that I don't know how many steps we
想要考虑，但我们相处得很好
want to think of taking but we get quite
这里的小数字尤其如此
small numbers here especially yeah so
一旦我们在这里得到一些小数字
once we get small numbers here little
小量的
Epsilon's
这是每个人的小写速记
that's everybody's shorthand for small
数字你期望什么
numbers what what would you expect to
在对角线上看到特征值
see on the diagonal the eigenvalues
因为它具有与之相同的特征值
because this has the same eigenvalues as
这就是这个和这些一点点
this as this is this and these little
epsilon沙皇不会改变
epsilon czar not going to change the
特征值太多，所以这些将会开启
eigenvalues too much so these will be on
对角线将接近
the diagonal will be close to the
特征值实际上发生了什么
eigenvalues and actually what happens is
这是第一个
this one comes first
首先我想这个是非常准确的
that one is quite accurate first I guess
我们应该做一个简单的例子
we should probably do a simple example
看到这种情况实际上我做了一个
to see this happen actually I do an
注释中的例子，让我说一下
example in the notes and let me say what
发生了所以我做了两个两个例子
happens so I do a two by two example
这有点像costheta正弦
which has something like cos theta sine
theta哦，我不知道我是什么
theta oh I don't know what I've
忘了我拿了什么，我没有
forgotten what I took and I don't have
那里有一个人的笔记
that page of notes here somebody here
这里的东西在这里
something here something here
作为一个不是，然后一个刚刚
as a as a not and then a one after just
一步有正弦立方体那里和
one step has sine cubed theta there and
那里的数字越来越多了
numbers there that are getting a much
更接近特征值对不起这个
closer to the eigenvalue sorry that this
这不是一个全面的例子，而是重点
isn't a full-scale example but the point
这个例子就是这个
of the example is here that this this
关闭对角线元素得到了被立方和
off diagonal entry got gets cubed and
下一步将是第九步
the next step will it'll be its ninth
权力，然后是第27个权力所以它
power and then the 27th power so it's
真的很快就会到0而且这个
really quickly going to 0 and this
这是因为立方收敛是这样的
happens so with the cubic convergence is
你知道这是一个数字奖
you know that's a prize in numerical
线性代数就这样发生了
linear algebra so that's that happened
好的，所以这就到了现场
okay so this arrived on the scene and
迅速吹掉所有其他方法
quickly blew away all other methods that
被用来计算特征值
were being used to compute eigenvalues
但数字人就是他们自己
but numerical people being what they are
他们希望提高它喜欢的是有
they wanted to improve it like is there
一个办法让它更快，横空出世
a way to make it faster and turned out
事实证明，这更好
there is it turned out that the better
方式基本上是相同的想法，但只是你
way basically the same idea but just you
知道你总是在寻找一个简单的
know you're always looking for a simple
改变，这是想法
change and it was the idea of
尝试并转向引入转变
introducing a shift was tried and turned
出去工作非常好所以这样
out to work extremely well so so that's
这样的改进让我们知道了
the improvement so so we take a one know
那么这种转变是如何运作的呢？
so how does it how does this shift work
如果我有空间，而不是不是我
so instead of a not i if i got space
在这里做这个而不是结我
here to do do this instead of a knots i
不要
take a not
-转移所以转移是一些倍数
- shift so shift is some multiple of the
如果我只是移动一个矩阵的身份
identity if I just move a matrix by a
身份的多重性发生了什么
multiple of the identity what happens to
它的特征向量会发生什么
its eigenvectors what happens to its
特征值非常简单
eigenvalues something pretty simple
对，因为我只是换了si
right because I'm just shifting by si
他们的特征向量会发生什么
what happens to its eigenvectors they're
同样的这个以及发生了什么
the same this and what happens to the
如果a，它们的特征值会改变
eigenvalues they change by s this if a
不是v等于lambdav然后当我
not v equal lambda v then when I
将此乘以V将有一个
multiply this by V there will be an
额外它将是lambda减去s因为
extra it'll be lambda minus s because
V的身份时间就是V，所以
the identity times the V is just V so so
它只是移动所有的特征值
the it just shifts all the eigenvalues
通过s，你试图转移你寻找一个
by s and you try to shift you look for a
转移你如果你这将是伟大的
shift you this would be great if you
我知道lambdana会在那里转移
knew lambda n a shift there you would be
寻找0，那么如果他们转移
looking for 0 then if you shifted them
所有这些lambda都证明了这一点
all by that lambda and it turns out that
会加快速度，所以你工作
would speed things up so so it you work
而现在我用这个矩阵代替
instead with this matrix as now I'm
我再考虑Q无效R
again I'm factoring in the Q naught R
没有，所以这是方法的工作
naught so that's the work of the method
在每一步都在做克施密特
is in doing gram-schmidt at every step
然后有一点工作
and then there's a little work in
颠倒顺序然后我想
reversing the order and then I want to
撤消班次，所以我这样做
undo the shift so I so you do that
因素分解现在让我们看看你可能有
factorization now let's see you may have
帮助我记住我应该做的事情
to help me to remember what I should do
在这里，我将那些与我相反​​的因素分解
here so I factor those I reverse those
然后我想我补充了这个转变
and then I think I add back the shift
这是我的一个1，所以我花了我点头
and that's my a 1 so I took a nod I
转移它，我工作了它是
shifted it I worked with it q are
颠倒顺序是q加回来了
reversed the order are q added back the
转移得到一个矩阵，我是什么
shift to get a matrix and what what am i
当然希望
of course hoping of
矩阵a1，他们不是我希望的
the matrix a 1 and they not I'm hoping
他们仍然相似，我希望如此
they're still similar I'm hoping so I
做了一个转变，我解除了转变，但是
did a shift and I undid a shift and but
当然，在我做了QR之后
of course after after doing a QR I have
去检查
to check
这些真的仍然相似所以让我
are these really still similar so let me
试着再次检查一下我能不能
just try to check that one again can i
也许我只是坐在那里
maybe I'll just it's sitting right there
所以让我再做一次，我希望如此
so let me do it again I'm hoping that
我希望你知道的地方
I'm hoping that something you know where
我们改变了哦是的我们在这里展示了
did we change oh yeah here we showed
即A1是类似于一个结，我
that a1 was similar to a knot and I'm
希望甚至可能仍然如此
hoping that's probably still true even
你知道这种转变并没有弄乱
you know the the shift didn't mess that
我们只是尝试所以不是没有那个R
up let's just try so ain't no a that's R
没问题，没有加上si好了，现在
naught Q naught plus si okay and now
我要做什么我会去做什么
what am I going to do I'm going to what
在我弄清楚Q之前我做了什么
did i do before I figured out what Q
没有人是你从此记得如此
naught was from this you remember so so
这是我们的结，现在我必须放入Q.
this is our knot now I have to put in Q
没问题，但问题就是这件事
naught but Q naught is this thing
反向时间这是可行的
inverse times this is this gonna work
我想要我，但我不认为我
I'm I'm like hoping but I don't think I
想要得到它，不，不是没有问题
wanted to get that no it's not Q naught
那里有什么我放在这里，如果它
there what what do I put here and if it
不起作用我们会留下它
doesn't work we'll leave it as an
运动好，所以是的因为我没有
exercise okay so yeah cuz I didn't I
并没有某种方式开始
didn't sort of start right somehow
好吧，但让我继续前进
okay so but let me just push along to
看看会发生什么，所以我正在插电
see what happens so I'm I'm plugging in
对于Q在这里，我正在插入这个
for Q naught here I'm plugging in this
矩阵所以它不应该是
matrix so it shouldn't have been
颠倒它的时间并不相反
inverted it times are not inverse
谁知道它可能工作，谁知道这么
who knows it might work who knows so
这是没有问题的，也不是
that's the R naught Q naught right or is
每个人都跟我抱歉这个R.
everybody with me sorry about this R
没有逆，然后我必须添加s
naught inverse and then I have to add s
我，我做了什么
I so what have I done
我只是喜欢相信这一点
I'm just like pushed on believing that
这会起作用，因为它就是
this would work because it it's the
现在经常使用的方法
method that that is constantly used now
我有什么我有有它
do I have what do I have there is it
工作这是我们的不是
working this is our not a that was of
当然没有任何结果
course a naught R naught a naught R
没有逆R没有一个R
naught inverse R naught a naught R
没有反正的减去什么的
naught inverse good minus s what's
什么是我从那里得到的
what's what have I got there from from
不是-不知道那是什么
the are not - si R naught what is that
那是-我看起来很成功他们不是
that's - si I look success they are not
取消它们不是反向所以这个
cancels they are not inverse so this
该术语来自那个-
that term from from that that that is -
SI取消+S我完成哎哟
si cancels + s I am finished and lo and
看，我们有相同的相似性，所以我们
behold we have the same similarity so we
被多个人搞乱了
messed around by a multiple of the
身份并没有它实际上
identity and it didn't it it actually
如果我们这样做会使事情更快收敛
makes the thing converge faster if we
选择好的转变，但基本上
choose the shifts well and but basically
同样的想法仍然正常工作，所以这是
the same idea still working ok so that's
这就是QR方法以及这就是
that's the QR method well that's the
方法我们没有显示，也没有显示
method we haven't shown and won't show
除了这一半完成了
that except for this half half completed
例如，我不打算证明这一点
example we I don't plan to to prove that
下三角形部分开始
the lower triangular part begins to
消失
disappear
变小和小和
gets smaller and smaller and smaller and
那么特征值上弹出
then the eigenvalues pop up on the
对角线它是惊人的惊人的好吧
diagonal it's it's amazing amazing okay
现在我们还有其他改进吗？
now is there any other improvement we
可以做到这样的方法和地点
can make so that's the method and where
是工作和使用该方法
is the work and in using that method
因为那是我们一直关注的
because that's what we always focus on
我们在哪里花费电脑时间
where we spending computer time
好吧，我们花了很多时间在电脑上
well we're spending computer time in
做分数所以它
doing the doing the factorization so it
没有任何费用可以转移
didn't cost anything to shift by the
身份，但我们不得不考虑到这一点
identity but then we had to factor that
在QnaughtRnaught然后它没有
in the Q naught R naught then it didn't
花费很多钱来增加它们
cost much to multiply them in the
相反的顺序所以工作是在QR所以
opposite order so the work was in Q R so
我们能想到任何改进的事吗？
could we think of anything to improve
我想我能想到的那个方面
that aspect I think could we think of
什么都有，然后我们有一个
anything there and then we've got a
如果是真的一流的方法
really first class method well if the
矩阵我知道我们开始的矩阵
matrix a I know ik the matrix we started
有一些零允许我们
with had some zeros that that allowed us
跳过执行QR的步骤
to skip steps in doing the QR
因素分解所以我要说的是什么
factorization so so what am I gonna say
我要说一个或不是我们的原创
I'm gonna say if a or a not our original
矩阵有一堆零，让我们说
matrix has a bunch of zeros let's say
它有一大堆零的有
it's got a whole lot of zeros there
也许这很好我在这里过度了我
maybe it's well okay I overdid it here I
知道特征值，但是和
know the eigenvalues right off but and
所以说实话，我不能这么说
so the truth is I can't that saying that
如果它不会发生，但我们
if that it's not going to happen but we
可以用一个额外的对角线得到零
can get zeros with one extra diagonal
事实证明这是主要的
that turns out so that here's the main
对角大家
diagonal everybody
把目光投向主对角线和
got his eye on the main diagonal and and
如果我能得到很多，那就是一个对角线
and one diagonal if I can get a lot of
零，但我不能通过简单的计算
zeros but I can't by simple computation
所以我会告诉你如何得到一个，但我
so I'll show you how to get one but I
无法将所有负载都归零，因为
can't get all loads to be zero because
然后我会让特征值合适
then I would have the eigenvalues right
在那里，那我怎么知道我
there and that well how do I know that I
难道你不知道在淘汰
can't you know in an elimination
普通的解决斧头等于你真的
ordinary solving ax equal B you really
确实达到了上三角形式
do get to an upper triangular form right
一些运营商有些消除
some operator some some elimination
你插走的步骤和你的矩阵
steps you plug away and your matrix
成为上三角你和你
becomes upper triangular you and you're
金色
golden
但这太过于期待了
but that's too much to expect here in
事实上我们知道我们不能简单地做到这一点
fact we know we can't do it by simple
步骤因为如果我们能做到的话
steps because if we could do it
如果我们能和你一起去找你
if we could get to a you with with a
整个下三角部分为零
whole lower triangular part zero we
会发现特征值和我们
would have found the eigenvalues and we
知道特征值解决了一个系统
know that the eigenvalues solve a system
求解n次方程式和我们
solve an equation of nth degree and we
知道有人证明了一个世纪以来的世纪
know somebody proved centuries a century
或者更久以前你无法解决的问题
or more ago that you can't solve an
我们瞬间将它简单地等同于一点
instant we equate in by simple little
正确的步骤，你知道这是谁和
steps right do you know who that was and
并且你知道那个事实和
and that you know that fact and and and
它适用于什么程度
what degree does it apply to so that's
你有点重要的事实
an important fact in that you sort of
接受数学，是的，你是什么
pick up in in math yeah what are you
第五度啊所以5×5和
fifth degree yeah so five by five and
这将是不可能的
and up would be this is impossible
不可能不可能没有公式
impossible impossible there's no formula
找到一个简单的公式为
to find a simple formula for the for the
lambda表达式
lambdas
并且类似地，天鹅座的
and similarly for the Cygnus the
奇异的价值所以论证是
singular values so the argument is
绝对是一种难度
definitely a level of difficulty beyond
ax等于B逆矩阵或
ax equal B the inverse matrix or
东西枢轴所有你能做的
something the pivots all that you can do
确切地说，如果你做我们的算术
exactly if you do exact arithmetic we
找不到lambdas，但我们
cannot find the lambdas exactly but we
因为我们希望能够得到尽可能接近再见
can get as close as we like bye-bye
继续使用QR方法，所以是的
continuing with the QR method so yes in
换言之，所以我们不能让我们不得不
other words so we can't get we have to
如果我们想要喜欢的话，我会满足于此
settle for if we want to like at the
我们之前开始改进我们的矩阵
beginning improve our matrix before we
开始做那些我们可以得到的东西
start doing that stuff we can get it
有一个额外的对角线，你知道吗？
with one extra diagonal and do you know
什么样的矩阵
what kind of a matrix
什么名字，我不知道为什么
what whose name and I don't know why
是的再说一遍
yeah say it again
鞋帮hessenburg所以鞋帮就像
upper hessen burg so upper is just like
上三角形它在那里，但关键
upper triangular it's up there but key
正如我所说，这个人的名字是Hessen出生的
person's name is Hessen birth i as i say
我就是这样的Hessenbert矩阵
i'm that's a Hessen bert matrix so
hesterberg矩阵是一个矩阵
hesterberg matrix is a matrix with one
三角加一个对角但是
triangular plus one more diagonal but
很多零，你知道N的顺序
lots of zeros you know order of N
像几乎一半的东西平方
squared something like almost like half
N平方不大，但接近零
N squared not quite but but close zeros
你能不能证明那些
and you would you could show that those
零在QR中保留为零
zeros stay zeros in Q R so that that
真的得到回报它减少削减了
really pays off it cuts the cuts the
努力工作，这是
work down significantly so that's the
完整的QR方法是第一步减少一个
full QR method is is step one reduce a
到了esenberg形式的零和我
to esenberg form with a zeros and when I
说减少我的意思是找到相似之处
say reduce I mean find a similarity
改变当然因为我是我
transformation of course because I'm I
想要特征值
want the eigenvalues
这最终和他的我一样
this to end up the same as the his'n I
我希望保持与我相同的特征值
want to keep the same eigenvalues as I
去，然后第二步是QR就此
go and then step two is QR on this
HessenBurgh矩阵与芯片这样的
Hessen Burgh matrix with chips so that's
将编程的代码
the code that would would be programmed
在项目中，这就是MATLAB和嗯
in item a that's what MATLAB and well
真的MATLAB像其他人一样吸引人
really MATLAB is appealing like other
矩阵系统很有吸引力
matrix systems is appealing to la pack
和Linpack你认识的团队
and Linpack you you know the team of
一种专业的数值分析师
sort of professional numerical analysts
真的花了很多精力和时间
really spend a lot of effort and time
这本书有十位作者
that the book la pack has ten authors
而且你可以下载它
and and you it's you you can download
任何这些代码都像
any any of these codes like the
特征值代码，这就是matlab
eigenvalue code so that's what matlab
这就是matlab自然而然的地方
that's where matlab naturally that's
代码的圣经是好的，是的
sort of the Bible for codes in okay yeah
我觉得这很有趣
that's I think it's sort of interesting
知道并且还有一件好事
to know and there's one more good thing
告诉你这个方法和它
to tell you about this method and it
如果矩阵是对称的，则适用
applies if the matrix is symmetric if
如果我们检查，矩阵是对称的
the matrix is symmetric then if we check
所有这一切，我们可以发现，矩阵
all this we could find that the matrices
如果结是对称的则保持对称
stayed symmetric if a knot is symmetric
我可以检查你可以轻松检查
I can check you could easily check
通过这个，你会发现
through this and you will discover that
a1也是对称的，是的你可以
a1 is also symmetric yes you can it
原来你有一个你可以改写
turns out you have a you could rewrite
这具有Q零和Q化为乌有
this with a Q naught and a Q naught
反过来另一边但是Q.
inverse on the other side but that Q
没有逆是与Q无关
naught inverse is the same as Q naught
转置，因为它是正交的
transpose because it's an orthogonal
如果，矩阵和对称性将会失效
matrix and symmetry would fall out so if
它是对称的，而它是hessin中的N.
it's symmetric and the N it's in hessin
伯格形式，它保持对称
Burgh form and it stays symmetric at
什么可以告诉我什么的每一步
every step what what can you tell me
关于对称的esenberg矩阵
about a symmetric esenberg matrix it's
只有得到你只是擦除所有这些
only got yeah you just erase all these
如果那里有零，如果有
if there are zeros there and if the
矩阵是对称的然后我们可以安全
matrix is symmetric then we can safely
预测它只会有一个
predict that it will only have one
一个非零对角线上方的对角线
diagonal above one nonzero diagonal
实际上它会说主要的日子
above the main day in fact it will say
对称所以现在我应该写
symmetric so now I'll be should write
对称Katzenberg的矩阵和等于
symmetric Katzenberg's matrix and equals
三对角主要是三对角线
tri diagonal major yeah three diagonals
所以现在你真的减少了时间
so now you really have reduced the time
做QR，所以我说你有一个三
to do QR so I said you've got a tri
对角矩阵它将保持三对角线
diagonal matrix it'll stay tri diagonal
在所有这些步骤中，你正在工作
in all these steps so you're working
实际上只有三个n数
with just three n numbers well actually
两个因为它们在对角线上面而且
two n because they're diagonal above and
下面的对角线和你一样
the diagonal below are the same you're
只使用两个n数字
working with just two n numbers instead
N平方的顺序，它就像
of order N squared and it just goes like
一枚炸弹让我对称
a bomb so that's I for symmetric
矩阵，你看到它就是全部
matrices and you see that it was all
真的是那里的核心
based there really the heart of the the
算法的核心是QR好吧
heart of the algorithm was QR okay so
这是我的一半课程报告
that's my took half the class to report
在igwe找到的最喜欢的方式
on the favorite way to igwe to find
特征值哦我应该说些什么
eigenvalues oh I should say something
关于看到其他价值如此奇异
about seen the other values so singular
值当然是奇异值
values of course the the singular values
矩阵的特征值是a的特征值
of the matrix are the eigenvalues of a
转置一个
transpose a
平方根的平方根
square root square root of those
特征值，但你不会这样做
eigenvalues but you wouldn't do it that
你永远不会形成一个转置的方式
way you would never form a transpose a
好吧，我没有提到另一个
well I didn't mention that the other
你永远不会这样做的事情
thing you would never ever ever do so
让我把它放在这里就像在
let me just put it here this is like in
耻辱地解决这个问题
disgrace to solve that equation it's
好的，你知道回到一年级
like okay you know back to first grade
因为那不是很糟糕的
because that's not it's very bad a
决定因素首先是它
determinant come first of all it's
极其缓慢极为缓慢和
extremely slow extremely slow and
确定它正在打包这一切
determined it is packing all this
把信息放到最后
squared pieces of information into end
系数，它是绝望的
coefficients and it's hopelessly
病态，是的，你只是输了
ill-conditioned yeah you just you lose
所有信息的时间，所以它真的
information all the time so it's really
如果这是在相机上它更好
my if this is going on camera it better
和X一起去相机，因为它
go on camera with a with an X because it
不要这样做是的，所以我在哪里
don't do it okay yeah so where was I
奇异值，所以转置一个
singular values so a transpose a so
让我们再想想你能做些什么
again let's think about what you could
在开始之前开始做
do at the beginning before starting on
qr4用于转置a或用于矩阵
qr4 for a transpose a or for the matrix
什么你可以用正交做什么
a what what could you do with orthogonal
矩阵所以我猜我们做了什么
matrices so so I guess what what did we
说关于对称矩阵，所以这里
say about symmetric matrices so here's
我说过对称矩阵，如果
what I said about symmetric matrices if
你给我一个对称矩阵我可以在
you give me a symmetric matrix I can in
只需简单的一些简单步骤
just a simple number of simple steps
使它成三角我无法做到
make it tri diagonal I can't make it
对角线，因为那时我会找到
diagonal because then I'd be finding the
特征值和亚伯是第一个
eigenvalues and Abel who was the first
有人看到这是不可能的
person to see that that was impossible
会禁止的
would would forbids it
但是让我让我写下来的是什么
but so what let me let me write down
如果我有一个，我在这说什么
what I'm saying here if I have a
对称矩阵S
symmetric matrix s
我可以找到一堆Q和Q.
I can find a bunch of Q's and Q
转置，我可以把它们全部
transpose and I can put them all
一起成为一个大Q和它
together into one big Q and it's
转置以及我对此有何了解
transpose and what do I know about the
该矩阵的特征值只是Q
eigenvalues of that matrix let's just Q
是正交总是那么你能做什么
is orthogonal always so what can you
告诉我你的情况和Q一样
tell me about thee this is the same as Q
sQ逆，因此是本征
s Q inverse and therefore the eigen
值是它类似于它同
values are the same it's similar to it
我发现它变成了三角形
and it becomes tri diagonal after I find
一个好的q现在，因此同样的lambdas
a good q now and therefore same lambdas
哪个三角形与同一个lambdas
which tri diagonal with the same lambdas
现在我在想什么约我在这里
now what am I thinking about here I'm
想着告诉我相应的
thinking about tell me the corresponding
关于我想要的奇异值的可能性
possibility about singular values I want
现在，我正在为我的矩阵做点什么
to do something to my matrix now I'm I'm
总是采用一般矩阵a而我
always taking a general matrix a and I'm
寻找它的奇异价值，我
looking for its singular values and I'm
希望简化它，我是什么
looking to simplify it and what am I
允许做是的我想我的问题
allowed to do yeah I guess my question
是相似的转变离开了
is similarity transformations left the
单独的特征值我能做什么呢
eigenvalues alone what can I do that
独自离开了奇异值这
leaves the singular values alone that's
一个根本问题，因为它是如此
a fundamental question because it was so
做的特征值的基础
fundamental for eigenvalues by doing
这是一个矩阵，它与我相反
this a matrix and it's inverse I got
类似的东西，即使在即时检查
something similar and ie checked even in
这个类的特征值相同
this class that the eigenvalues same
lambda表达式
lambdas
现在我想在结束了整条生产线
now I want a whole line that ends up
和Sigma一样，我想要你
with the same Sigma's and I want you to
告诉我我被允许做什么
tell me what I'm allowed to do to the
矩阵而不改变Sigma的
matrix without changing the Sigma's
这是一个也许不要喊出来
that this is a maybe don't shout it out
马上让每个人都想到了什么
immediately let everybody think what am
我允许对每个矩阵做一个矩阵
I allowed to do to a matrix every matrix
我有这些奇异的价值观
has got these singular values and now I
想要使它成为一个更好的矩阵
want to make it a better matrix with
如果我做的话，更多零或什么的
more zeros or something if I if I do
那就是它
that to it
这会改变西格玛的能力吗？
does that change the Sigma's can I do
不仅如此，我还能做些什么
more than that to it what can I do it
什么样的矩阵将有什么
what what group of matrices will have
同样的西格玛作为我的起始矩阵a
the same Sigma's as my starting matrix a
所以这是一个基本的基本问题
so that's a basic basic question about
关于看到他们的价值观和
that about seeing their values and the
SVD让我们，让我们觉得答案
SVD so let's let's think of the answer
一起好吧所以它已经连接起来了
together okay so it's got it's connected
到SVD所以让我记住SVD
to the SVD so let me remember the SVD
SVD我有一些正交矩阵
the SVD I have some orthogonal matrix
那么矩阵SV的奇异值
then the singular value of the matrix SV
强迫他们的价值观，然后另一个
force into their values and then another
正交矩阵我能做些什么
orthogonal matrix what could I do to
那个不会触及这个的等式
that equation that would not touch this
伙计，所以我问的是什么不变性
guy so I'm asking what invariance
因为不接触它意味着离开它
because not touching it means leaving it
不变，所以我在寻找什么
on not varying so I'm looking for what
在什么操作下是什么
what under what operations are the
我的奇异值不变
singular values invariant when I was
看着特征值，这就是
looking at eigen values this was the
操作很好，它不一定是
operation well it didn't have to be
正交的东西然后是逆的
orthogonal something then it's inverse
但现在又是什么呢
but now what is it up there what what
我可以做那个矩阵吗？
could I do to that matrix a could I
当我投入时，我可以乘以Q
multiply by Q could I when I throw in
有问题，甚至可能在另一方面
there Q it may be not even on the other
如果我输入正交Q，我会结束
end if I if I throw in an orthogonal Q
我可以改变奇异值吗？
do I change the singular values or do I
不改变根本问题
not change the fundamental question the
答案是
answer is
不，我不改变他，我被允许做
no I don't change him I'm allowed to do
因为这是一个正交矩阵
that because here's an orthogonal matrix
水性时候，你如果这两个都
aq times you if both of those are
正交然后产品是对的
orthogonal then the product is right
大家都知道，如果是两个产品
everybody knows that if a product of two
正交矩阵仍然是正交的
orthogonal matrix is still orthogonal
更好地知道我不知道是的
better know that I don't know that yeah
所以，如果我有一个正交矩阵Q和
so if I have an orthogonal matrix Q and
一个正交矩阵我声称这个
an orthogonal matrix u I claim that this
仍然是抱歉，我该如何检查
is still what sorry and how do I check
好吧我用了一些测试
it well I use some tests for
正交性会是什么
orthogonality what would be that what
测试你喜欢使用逆是
tests you like to use the inverse is the
和转置一样你喜欢那样吗？
same as the transpose do you like that
测试所以我会反转它Qu逆
test so I'll invert it Q u inverse of
当然对于任何U逆Q的矩阵
course for any matrix that's U inverse Q
反过来但这些是分开的
inverse but these were separately
正交使得U转置Q.
orthogonal so that's U transpose Q
转置，这与Qu相同
transpose and that is the same as Q u
转置是的所以我使用了
transpose yeah so I used the
U的正交性和正交性
orthogonality of U and the orthogonality
Q得出结论反过来是
of Q to conclude that the inverse is the
转置所以答案是肯定的我可以
transpose so the answer is yes I could
现在用奇异的价值来做
do that now with singular value with
特征值我不得不繁殖
eigenvalues I had to I had to multiply
上由Q逆或Q的另一侧
on the other side by Q inverse or Q
转置，我现在必须这样做
transpose do I have to do that now no
我能做些什么在右边我
what can I do on the right-hand side I
可以乘以我可以不管它
can multiply by I can leave it alone
那么它具有相同的奇异值
then it has the same singular values
因为如果我，那就是那个sigmund
because it's the same sigmund there if I
有一个正交矩阵乘以
have a orthogonal matrix times the
正交的对角线倍
diagonal times of orthogonal that
对角线是正对角线
diagonal is positive diagonal is going
是西格玛现在还等什么我可以做
to be Sigma now so what what can I do on
这方面我可以乘以任何
this side I can multiply by any
哦，这一切都在矩阵上
oh it's all going on matrix on that side
太让我们把这个家伙Q1，这
too so let's call this guy q1 and this
伙计q2我还是有一个
guy q2 I'm still I still have an
正交矩阵它们是正交的
orthogonal matrix they're orthogonal
矩阵在那里和相同的西格玛弹出
matrix there and the same Sigma popped
在中间这就是你的意思
in the middle so that's what you're
允许这样做可以给我们更多的自由
allowed to do that gives us more freedom
在我们必须做的事情之前
before we got when we had to do
具有相同的相似变换
similarity transformations with the same
我们得到它是三角形但是现在
guy we got it to be tri diagonal but now
我们被允许做更多的事情
we're allowed to do more stuff we're
允许使用不同的正交
allowed to use different orthogonal
左边和右边的矩阵和我们
matrices on the left and right and we
可以从三进一步减少它
can reduce it even further from tri
对角线由斜的，因此这样的
diagonal to by diagonal so the so the
第一步是0步骤
first step is getting 0 the the step of
越来越零降低它一路
getting zeros reduces it all the way to
那里有所有的零，所以它是
that with all the zeros there so it's
然后我就更容易了
it's it's easier then then I work on
这，这是我利用工作矩阵
this this is the matrix I work on using
QR类型的想法有些像
a QR type idea some some method like
所以每个人都看到我们是这样的
that so so everybody's seeing that we're
我们的算法得到两个
taking where our algorithm is got two
阶段一是得到很多零和得到
stages one is get a lot of zeros and get
他们在那些将保持零的地方
them in places that will stay zero as
第二部分算法开始了
part two of the algorithm gets going and
然后运行你想要的算法的第二部分
then run part two of the algorithm you'd
其染色的每个步骤是非常快的
stain with its each step is very fast
现在因为做QR分解了
now because doing a QR factorization is
快，但有一个问题，是的，是的
fast but was there a question yeah yep
所以我会称之为
so this would I would call this by
对角线当然和每个人
diagonal of course and everybody
我认识到如果我有一个对角线
recognizes that if I have a by diagonal
矩阵称之为或不是或等等
matrix call it a or a not or whatever
转移你怎么想？
then a transfer what do you think about
转置a
a transpose a
如果那是一个转置的话会是什么？
what would a transpose a if that was a
什么你能告诉我一个转
what could you tell me about a transpose
你能不能像矩阵那样乘以矩阵
a could you multiply matrices like
知道非零的位置
knowing that where the non zeros are
喜欢在你的头脑中，并了解
like in your head and get an idea of
如果我有一个对角线矩阵那么所以
where so if I have a by diagonal matrix
一个那么几分含蓄的SVD我
a then sort of implicitly in the SVD I'm
看一个转置a和什么会
looking at a transpose a and what would
我对转置的看法是真实的
I what would be true about a transpose a
这将是三角形所以我所做的
it would be tri diagonal so what I've
在这里完成，我刚刚在那里完成了
done here and what I've done there just
如果你匹配你可以歌剧
match up you can you can opera if you
不想改变你的奇异价值
don't want to change singular values you
可以一路到这里，但后来
can get all the way to here but then to
找到那些他们价值观的东西
find those thing of their values that
将涉及转置它将是
would involve a transpose a it would be
对称和三对角然后
symmetric and tri diagonal and then
你会在那场比赛中右好了，
you'd be in that game right okay so
这就是Ag的基本事实
that's those are the basic facts of Ag
和SVD的顺序为a的矩阵
and SVD for matrices of order up to a
千说我不知道​​我还不够
thousand say I don't know I'm not enough
专家知道哪里更高
of an expert to know where higher
因为在完美的数学中它是
because the in in perfect math it's
要采取无限的步骤或阿巴
gonna take infinitely many steps or Abba
他会的，会非常惊讶
would be very surprised right he would
看到你解决特征值和
see you solving for eigenvalues and
通过一大堆的瞬间方程
instantly equation by a whole lot of
小步骤，准确地得到它们
little steps and getting them exactly
正确的，这不会发生，但你让他们
right that won't happen but you get them
在epsilon中的许多步骤
within epsilon in a number of steps
这就像n立方体那么漂亮
that's like n cubed so that's pretty
令人印象深刻的特征值问题是
impressive the eigenvalue problem is
用a引用来解决引用
being solved in quotes by by an out by a
快速的方法，这会让你
fast method that that that gets you a
在n立方体的公差范围内的良好答案
good answer within a tolerance in n cube
正确的步骤，这样就可以了
steps right so that's great as long as
一个不是
an isn't too
然后当n太大时
and then when n is too big which of
当然，你必须再考虑一下
course happens you have to think again
所以这种方法将是一个巨人
so this method will be is a giant
然后，成功到大型矩阵
success up to large matrices but then
你必须再思考一下，是什么
you have to think again and what is
我猜想再次参与思考
involved in thinking again well I guess
更多的思考如果你做了什么
more thinking so what do you do if the
矩阵更大
matrix is bigger
我猜那个克里洛夫的下一个
I guess that the next that that Krylov
会说使用我的方法所以克里洛夫会
would say use my method so Krylov would
特别是如果你的矩阵很稀疏
say especially if your matrix was sparse
我们能记住Krylov是什么吗？
can we just remember what Krylov was
克雷洛夫以矢量b开头
Krylov started with a vector b
乘以乘以a乘以
multiplied it by a multiply that by a
并起身让我们说到999B
and got up to let's say a to the 999 B
所以现在他得到了我们出关叫道它的
so now he's got us out cried off it's
他有一个千维空间
got a thousand dimensional space he's
有一千个载体的基础
got a basis for it thousand vectors that
跨越千维空间和
span a thousand dimensional space and
他将着眼于只在该矩阵
he'll look at the matrix a only on that
换句话说，我不会进入空间
space in other words I won't go into
关于他的细节限制了
detail about that he restricts the
这个千维的矩阵
matrix to this thousand dimensional
空间，他希望它能抓住我们
space and he hopes that it's captured we
但我们希望，特征向量
it we hope that the eigenvector is
几乎几乎在那个空间和
almost virtually in that space and
实际上我不会不去
actually I wouldn't wouldn't go up to
让我从那百人中拿出九分
let me take a nine out of that hundred
维度可能会抓住
dimensional would probably catch the
特征向量，如果特征向量是
eigenvector so if the eigenvector is
几乎在这个空间，我们可以看
virtually in this space then we can look
在一个数百万的矩阵我们可以
at a matrix of order a hundred we can
把它放下来看看它的行动
bring a down to just see its action on
那个空间和任何一块如此
that space and any piece of so when so
这是一个所以我看看矢量V
here's a so I look at vectors V which
是一些组合C1B
are some combination C 1 B
加C到B加C3平方B和C.
plus C to a B plus C 3 a squared B and C
100到99到B再加上一个错误
100 a to the 99 to B plus it an error
我会忽略那个错误，因为
and I'm gonna ignore that error because
我已经走了，我已经达到100维了
I've gone I've got up to dimension 100 I
可能会说是非常安全的忽略
probably say is pretty safe to ignore
那个错误，然后在这个空间
that error and then in this space just
无论在哪里，都要看矩阵
looking at the matrix a so wherever a to
第100个进入忘记它
the 100th comes in forget it
只要想想矩阵a就像
just think about the matrix a as as
在这里乘以这种矢量
multiplying vectors of this kind in this
空间然后我有一百个百
space then I have a hundred by hundred
也许我可以重视一个问题，你知道
maybe I can value a problem and you know
大矩阵a被简化为矩阵
the big matrix a is reduced to a matrix
大小100你看到了什么
of size 100 by do you see sort of what
我是说，即使d我不是
I'm saying even though the D I'm not
给人的细节，是想的
giving the details that that think of a
一个大小一百万的矩阵的东西
thing of a matrix a of size a million
然后你将它应用于Krylov载体，所以我
and you apply it to Krylov vectors so I
称他们为Krylov矢量小K.
call them little K for a Krylov vector
在这个百维空间中如此
in this hundred dimensional space so
他们有一百万减100零
they have a million minus 100 zero
组件，你可以说这没关系这
components you could say this okay this
在Krylov空间这是一百万
is in the Krylov space this is a million
K一百
K a hundred
哦，它是一个完整的有一个它有一个
oh it's a full there's a it's got a
百万组件，但它只是
million components but it's out of just
一个百维空间，所以当我
a hundred dimensional space so when I
乘以它就会有它
multiplied by a it'll have it'll be
大多数情况下，部分在Krylov
mostly in mostly in partly in the Krylov
空间K数百和一块出的K
space k hundreds and a piece out of K
100，我只是忽略了那一部分
100 and I just ignore that part of the
矩阵所以我有一百一百
matrix so I have a hundred by hundred
问题，我解决了找到
problem and I solve the find the
特征值，它们非常好
eigenvalues and they're pretty good
近似于特征值
approximation to the eigenvalues to the
可我希望喜欢的最低百
may i hopefully like the lowest hundred
特征值我想知道但是我
eigenvalues i'd like to know that but i
可能不确定这个想法会不会
might not be sure that this idea would
给我第一个最低的百分之一
give me the lowest hundred the first
一百个特征值
hundred eigenvalues of the of the
百万阿玛丽亚的矩阵我是
million of the matrix of size Amelia I'm
这里只需几分钟
just taking a few minutes here to to
那种波什么克雷洛夫手中
sort of wave hands about what Krylov the
克里洛夫的想法会做，我可能
Krylov idea would do and I probably
本学期不会再提Krylov了
won't mention Krylov again this semester
所以它能做的就是看看这个
so what it can do is look at this
特殊类型的空间，因为我们可以
particular type of space because we can
快速获得它的基础
get a basis for it quickly just multiply
我们可以一次又一次地
again and again by a then we can
正交化这个基础
orthogonalize that basis
这是某种形式的克施密特
that's gram schmidt in some some form
我们总是回到盛大
we're always going back to a grand
施密特然后我有一百一百
Schmitt then I have a hundred by hundred
我有一个大小为a的子空间
I have a bate a subspace of size a
一百个我看着Mait为了什么
hundred I look at the Mait for what the
矩阵在那个空间里做，我
matrix does in that space and that I
可以找我能找到特征值
could look for I could find eigenvalues
被限制在那个空间他们
were restricted to that space they
不会是完美的特征值但是
wouldn't be the perfect eigenvalues but
他们会准确的好，所以我没有
they would be accurate okay so I didn't
知道它会采取一个班时间
know it would take one class time to
谈论寻找特征值和特征
talk about finding eigenvalues and
奇异的价值，但我们做了一些
singular values but we did some
我们记得那些重要的事情
important things we remembered that
相似性是检查事物的事情
similarity is the thing to check thing
保存，因为它不会改变
to preserve because it doesn't change
特征值，然后我们
the eigen values and then we
对于奇异的价值观是什么
for singular values what was the thing
你可以乘左右的
you could multiply left and right by
不同的正交矩阵和
different orthogonal matrices and
不知怎的，也许没有
somehow maybe that doesn't have a
已建立的名称乘以左和
established name multiplying left and
通过q1和aq2转换是的
right by a q1 and a q 2 transpose yeah
但但这个想法是明确的，
but but the idea is clear and that
不改变我们的奇异值
doesn't change the singular values we're
准备现在变成真实的，也许
ready to move now into real and maybe
我们下一步我们不花钱
our next step which we don't spend a
很长一段时间会像随意的
long time on will be like random
如果您的矩阵是正确的，那么采样
sampling what if your matrix is just way
太大
too big
所以这是一个新的非常新的想法很
so that's a new very new idea very
数值线性的不同想法
different idea in numerical linear
代数就是对矩阵进行采样
algebra is just to sample the matrix
你能相信答案吗？
could you believe that the answer is
要出来吧
going to come out right
只是随机抽样的几率
just for a random sample well the odds
对你有好处，那就是那个
are in your favor okay so that's that'll
星期三然后我们有很多
be Wednesday and then we have lots of
new we'll move onward after that okay
新的我们之后好向前移动
看你周三谢谢
see your Wednesday Thanks